I'm Anthony Swofford.
author of the book Jarhead.
And I'm Bill Broyles. the screenwriter
of the movie with the same name.
So. Bill. I know a little bit
about your service in Vietnam...
but I'm wondering about when you joined
and where you served.
Well. it was a completely different context
'cause it was 1968...
and I had been in the anti-war movement...
and actually against the Vietnam War.
Then I got drafted...
and I couldn't get in the Coast Guard.
I tried to get. actually. to get into
George Bush's reserve unit...
but that was of course full to people like me.
And. of course.
I got sent immediately to Vietnam.
And I was an infantry. I had an infantry
platoon in the mountains for six months.
And. basically. I didn't see anybody
above the rank of captain...
and we were just off on our own.
The thing that attracted us to the movie so
much was the voice Tony had in the book.
So we thought. "Let's just start with that. "
And then we thought we'd show...
what happens to a young man...
when he's no longer a civilian.
And this is a memory that everyone
who's been in the Marines...
or any military will recognise instantly.
The guy with his head shaved...
standing in a line
with a bunch of people he's never met...
and being yelled at by his drill instructor.
An instantaneous change
in one's life. right?
Completely instantaneous. You suddenly
realise that everything you knew...
is meaningless.
Particularly. your girlfriend.
One day your mother
was making you fried eggs...
and the next day a pretty guy like this
is yelling obscenities in your ear.
And. you know. the thing is. the hardest
thing about going through boot camp...
is to keep a straight face.
'Cause if you laugh. you're dead.
And. of course. the other thing
that's introduced right here...
is that Swoff's father was in Vietnam.
Because the Vietnam echoes
are going to be all through this movie...
as they were through Tony's life.
And also this thing here
is of Tony and his girlfriend...
which is. again.
resonant throughout the movie.
What in the fuck is this?
Sir. it's a recruit's drawing
of a footlocker. sir!
And this is something
that I think every Marine realises...
shortly after putting his feet
on the boot steps.
Why the fuck
are you my scribe. then?
Isn't my scribe supposed to know
how to draw?
Sir. the recruit doesn't know!
The recruit thought the scribe
was supposed to write. sir!
Of course the recruit doesn't know!
This guy is great.
Yeah. this guy.
he's actually better than my drill instructor.
Show me exactly where your Skivvies
and running shoes go.
Sir. the recruit can't think...
while the drill instructor
is hitting him on his head. sir!
There's always a point about this
boot camp stuff. and the point here is...
you better learn to think
when things are going on all around you...
because if you can't...
you're going to be in serious trouble.
Sir. I got lost
on the way to college. sir!
And that's the beginning of the movie.
Welcome to the Marine Corps.
Mr Tony Swofford.
The drill instructor who replaced that guy...
who also abused a few other recruits...
and then got kicked out of
the drill-instructor position...
I ran into him in Austin. Texas. one time.
It was very bizarre.
Not all drill instructors are violent
with the recruits.
And he remembered that
that guy was out of hand...
and they had to send him
out of the training regiment.
Yeah. and we had fun with this scene...
because he's still this bright-eyed.
young recruit...
joining the Marine Corps.
which he dreamed about.
And so we thought
we'd put in this ridiculous song of an era...
Don't Worry. Be Happy...
as a counterpoint
to what's about to happen to him.
So much of this experience that Tony had...
was so true to my own experience...
and I think it's true
of my son's experience in Iraq. too.
There is such a universal quality
to this rite of passage. that...
the Swoff character's
going through right now.
Swofford.
What kind of fucking name is that?
It's English.
Tony. you should talk a little bit
about how...
your passage went
through the Marine Corps...
because we had to condense
a lot of Tony's story...
which took place over several years...
to make it. sort of. seem like
it's part of the dramatic unity of the movie.
Right. 'cause after boot camp ended...
I went to the School Of Infantry
and trained there...
and then was eventually sent
to the Fleet Marine Force...
which is this scene where I'm reporting
to Second Platoon Golf Company.
This is the world right here. boy.
You are plunged into it.
You know. it is a world that civilians
just don't know about.
It's so hard to explain to them
what it means to be a Marine.
And these guys are the hardcore guys
that have been in for a while...
and walking into their family
is this new recruit.
Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
May I help you?
And part of their distaste for him
is that he's a vision of themselves...
two or three years ago when they were
dumb enough to join. as well...
and to step into this crazy. insane world.
And that's one reason
that they play so many games with him.
Yeah. and I love this guy. too.
-Just. "You're welcome to second platoon. "
-Yeah.
"Fresh fucking meat. "
This is this very testosterone-driven
rite of passage...
to say. "Are you worthy. really?"
You know. not only what Tony says.
which was. you know...
"You're like what we looked like
when we were dumb enough to be here...
"but are you worthy to be one of us?"
And. it's not going to be easy
to become worthy.
Peter Sarsgaard just. sort of. walking
out of the group and coming over here is...
a really great. I think.
introduction of his character. too.
But these guys really have it down.
I have so many memories just like this...
and when I read Tony's book...
it was this resonance of how specific
his images and memories were to his war...
but how much they spoke to mine. as well.
Get some!
It's great that this movement to the darkness
in the barracks...
is kind of reawakening here.
When we were trying
to figure out how to do the movie...
there's so much rich stuff in Tony's book...
about what happened to him before the war
and why he joined the Marine Corps...
and we kept struggling with how to do this
and. of course...
some of the things you're getting here...
you know. the image of the brand
and the reference to the girlfriend...
some other little props and details that are
going to resonate through the movie...
are all set up here at the beginning.
If you want a brand. you've got to earn it.
Welcome to the Suck.
We're about to get to the point
where we've figured out...
let's try to find a way to talk about all
the stuff that was in Swoff's past...
but do it in a much more filmic way...
'cause we really wanted to stay
in the world of the Marine Corps.
Still got that stomach flu.
Swofford?
The structure of my book
couldn't be preserved for film...
but the montages. really. in some way...
echo some of my structure of the book.
And this is great. Sam's idea
of the doors closing and opening.
You know. we sort of worked our way
toward this later.
But I think it's very effective.
It has a little echo of The Godfather. too.
at the end of part one...
where the door closes on Michael.
But. you know.
I think that you get through this...
at least. our shorthand.
which I'm not sure is quite fair...
you know. completely.
to Tony's real family experience...
-but for the film....
-Right.
Yeah. I mean. that family montage
is possibly arch and a little extreme...
but. I think it does. you know.
in a few seconds...
the real work of telling the story.
The movement from my parents in bed...
in Honolulu...
and then the latter darkness.
that was part of my father's Vietnam service.
And also. there's the T-shirt again.
We were trying to set up these images...
and props that will resonate later.
You see his girlfriend putting on the T-shirt.
which we're going to see again and again.
And here. I love this entry of Jamie Foxx...
because the staff sergeants that I had
in the Marine Corps. who were just...
you know. I would follow anywhere.
this guy is it.
And he's kind of a composite character
of several sergeants...
that Tony meets through the course
of his Marine Corps career. but...
he is so true to the guys
that I knew in Vietnam. I mean...
that my son. in fact. is with now in Iraq.
But you can't have a military
without guys like this.
The younger guys. like I was. you know
you're going to leave the Marine Corps...
but you know these guys
are going to stay in for 22...
and they're somewhat foreign to you.
and you don't totally understand...
-that decision. They're lifers...
-They're lifers. Yeah.
...which is often derogatory. but...
the young Marine who sees a guy
like Jamie's character knows that...
you know. that he's a sound leader as well.
Indoc class starts on Monday.
I suggest you have your ass there.
Is that an order. Staff Sergeant?
It's a fucking opportunity.
It's a fucking honour.
It's the best fucking job
in the Marine Corps.
Sounds good. Staff Sergeant.
-Sounds good. Staff Sergeant!
-Sounds good.
Could I have my....
You know what? I got a better idea.
You play any instruments?
I played the trumpet in third grade.
"I played the trumpet in third grade.
Staff Sergeant. "
Community concerts.
And so you see this guy. this sergeant.
picking up on the fact...
that Swoff's not necessarily happy
about being in the Marine Corps...
eager to take advantage of this challenge
of being a scout sniper.
My pleasure.
Humiliation is a key part of the ritual
of being in the Marine Corps...
-as we've seen through the branding scene.
-Right.
And we're now about to get it...
what was the terrifying version. we're
now going to get the humorous version.
But it's the same sort of thing.
And it's the. you know.
his humiliation here....
This is sort of an amalgamated scene. too...
because. in fact. the Staff Sergeant...
Iooked at me and said. you know...
"You dumbass. there is no bugle job.
Get back in line. "
But that humiliation. that's part of
drawing someone into the group...
and if they can deal with it.
Okay. Swofford. play reveille.
And this is. of course. extremely funny.
You better play with your mouth.
Now. see. it's hard to comment....
As you try talking about this.
because. again...
part of the joy of writing
the screenplay for this...
is not only working with Tony's book.
but seeing what Sam and the actors...
did with what I wrote based on what he had
done and how they brought it to life.
'Cause this is so real. Just every detail...
Jamie's look.
the way he looks back to the men...
the way they are trying not to laugh.
In the book and in real life.
this happened in the desert...
and our First Sergeant...
-asked a couple guys.
-Yeah. it was to another guy.
And it was just such a good moment
that I just had to have it happen to Swoff.
And you had to humiliate me.
right. Broyles?
I did. Yeah. exactly.
Once I met Tony. I had to think...
of whatever possible humiliating positions
we could put him in. that would be great.
Will you shut the fuck up?
There is no bugle programme.
You sizzle-dick motherfucker.
Who do you think you are....
Part of the process of becoming a Marine
is to let go...
of the civilian values that you have...
including many of the really basic ones
of life and death.
"Thou shall not kill. " you know.
"I walk through the valley.... "
There's just several
biblical references here...
that are turned on their head.
And that's very common
in the Marine Corps. is that they want you...
to know that you're leaving behind
those things...
because if you keep them...
"Thou shall not kill. " you're gonna die...
and your friends are gonna die...
because you're in
a whole different world now.
It's a world civilians don't understand...
and. not only that...
you're in a world of the Marine Corps...
that's more elite than most Marine Corps
guys are going to understand.
So these guys are the elite of the elite.
Plus. we wanted to have some fun with this.
Oh. shit! Fuck. I can't see!
Back to the grunts. dick face!
In order to engage your target.
you must see your target....
The idea of the rhythms here...
is to deal with the extremes
of military experience. that is...
sometimes you're laughing. it's very funny...
and then. immediately.
you can go to pure terror and pure horror...
which is what's going to happen here.
All this sniper stuff comes
straight from you. you know.
-Just the things they are trying to learn.
-Yeah.
The shooting. of course. the ghillie suit....
And we see that the slow attrition
of these guys....
When I joined the platoon. there were about
40 guys who tried out for the platoon...
and six of us made it.
Yeah. again. that was Sam's idea.
to sort of keep inter-cutting the jogging...
with a smaller and smaller group.
Again. you know. this is also introducing
another character in this movie...
-which is the rifle.
-Right.
And the love affair with the rifle...
and you're going to hear things about it
that are going to play back again later.
But in the end. you have to trust your gut.
Details. gentlemen.
Details is gonna be the difference
between you killing your target...
and your target killing you.
We've all been taught that.
"Thou shalt not kill."
But hear this:
Fuck that shit!
This is meant to be disturbing...
and it's meant to be the introduction
to this rifle. which is a machine for killing.
And we spent a lot of time
behind the rifle like this.
What we have here.
is the making of the sniper...
which is the most important process
for me...
and for the making of. you know.
a guy who serves in the state platoon.
Fire. fire. fire.
This is a scene that didn't occur
in the book...
but. certainly. you know. sometimes...
training can be as dangerous as warfare...
and. unfortunately.
many people die a year from accidents.
And this was your idea. yeah. Bill?
Yeah. well. it was actually one of the guys
that came in...
told us this story. that something
like this happened in his training...
and I remembered it had happened
in mine. too. when we were working on .45.
And it really seemed like the kind of thing
that we wanted to introduce right away...
just how serious this is.
This is life and death.
And you better do
what you were trained to do.
You better learn. you better pay attention...
or there are serious consequences.
like right here.
Keep moving! Don't bunch up!
I can't! No!
-Cease-fire!
And this reaction of this guy...
of Jamie to this. is so true to life.
First. he's just so completely upset...
and then. he's just super pissed...
because this guy didn't listen to him...
-And he died.
-...and he died.
That's what really happens.
If you listened to me...
you would still be
fucking alive right now!
So we wanted to drain out all
the possible sentimentality out of this...
but. at the same time. leave the horror of it.
God help me.
You are now scout snipers.
This. to me. is one of the most poignant
moments in the whole movie...
and then to switch
to where they actually get their rifles.
This is the introduction of their rifle.
And. again.
we're setting up some verbal mantras...
and some visual images
that are going to pay off later.
Just whether it's the T-shirt
or the rifle or the Rifleman's Code.
You may now open your case.
pull out your M40A1 rifles.
And there's that tension there between...
Troy and Swoff over
who's been deemed the shooter.
Right.
Tony was a shooter in his team.
-This is my rifle.
-Boy. I remember saying this. Don't you?
-Yeah. Again and again.
I still can say it by heart. 30 years later.
Without my rifle. I am nothing.
-The Rifleman's Creed. right?
-Yeah. Exactly.
And you notice again
the sort of biblical things. is that...
we've dispensed with the traditional.
kind of biblical...
incantations that you believe as a civilian.
and you're given a new one...
that you have to believe as a Marine.
Not just as a convenience.
but as a practicality...
of keeping you alive
and keeping your friends alive.
Hit.
This is not just a Marine Corps movie.
These snipers are a whole other breed apart.
Which is one of the things
that make Tony's book so interesting...
because it distils
a lot of the military experience...
down to the essence of the violence...
which is. you know.
a man with a target in his reticle.
Yeah. you know.
one guy with a rifle and his partner....
There's a strange kind of simplicity
to the rifle. as well...
in a world of laser-guided bombs...
and cluster bombs and all the other.
sort of. larger machinery of war.
Good evening.
Iraq invaded and took over...
its tiny neighbour. Kuwait. today.
That set off worldwide protests
and drew sanctions...
from the United States.
Great Britain and the Soviet Union.
The government
of dictator Saddam Hussein...
claimed it went in at the invitation
of revolutionaries...
who had overthrown
the Kuwaiti government.
We have appealed to all our friends
around the world...
including the United States...
to come to our aid and assistance.
We're going to fucking war.
This is a scene
that when I read it in the book...
this is one of the moments that made me
want to do this as a movie...
because it's the effect of...
the films made about
the war I fought in for real...
on these guys of Tony's generation...
and the reactions of these guys
is so disturbing. but so true...
that they're just so juiced up by this...
but. at the same time. the undercurrent
underneath is absolute fear.
It's like. this is the moment they realise
that they're not just possibly going to war...
but they are going to war.
And so what do you think
watching this. Tony?
Yeah. it was....
You know. these films helped us...
kind of attach ourselves to that history...
and there's one way in which...
our base knowledge of war
was through these films.
This is what they're about to step into...
and they have to protect themselves...
and part of that protection is...
excitement. exhilaration. the possibility.
I love this shot. like the midnight showing
in The Rocky Horror Picture Show...
where they all know all the words...
they all see the things. They're seeing it
both technically and emotionally.
And that screen is like the protection.
Like. on the other side is their real war.
but right here is this one...
which they can watch safely.
This scene is so...
to the heart of what happens to you
and what you have to do.
And everyone could quote...
Apocalypse Now. Full Metal Jacket.
Platoon...
"I love the smell of napalm
in the morning"...
which is the scene right after this
in Apocalypse Now...
which is. for most people. shocking. but...
for young Marines. exciting.
And this is the moment
that they've been waiting for.
They're told they're going to war.
It's the moment they're waiting for
and the moment they're excited about...
but they're also terrified.
because they could not only kill. but die.
When I was in the Marines. you know.
we watched World War II movies.
When my father was in World War II.
he watched World War I movies.
Before that. people read books.
But you want to know how you're going
to do. "What am I going to be like?"
And then. my son. now.
is a pararescue jumper in the Air Force...
which is Special Operations guide.
He's on his third tour of Iraq.
and I'm hoping he'll get home in a week.
He's been in Afghanistan. as well.
And I. in fact.
did not encourage him to join the military...
he did that very much on his own...
but. of course.
I'm immensely proud of him...
and have my own very conflicting feelings
about the war in which he's in...
what his service is being used for.
And this is. like. the beginning
of the horniness that's evident.
Jake makes it totally evident
that they're about to go to a barren land.
Yeah. I'll say again. I think for Tony.
you know. we talked about this too. is that...
a lot of their Vietnam myths
that they saw in the movies...
it's all about the bar girls and the women...
just like for us it was all about
the French girls in World War II.
And here these poor guys
are going to where there's nobody.
There's no alcohol. there's no women.
there's no nothing. There's just the desert.
A large part of all military life...
in all combat and all wars...
is boredom in downtime...
and the guys in Vietnam
had the ville to go to...
to sort of fight some of that boredom.
and we were going to have nothing.
This is exactly how I went to war
in Vietnam. too.
-We got off of a Braniff airline jet.
-It's crazy.
Just like this. with the stewardess. saying.
"Goodbye. now. Good luck. now. "
And all of a sudden. you turn off the ramp.
and there you are.
And. you know. the light changes.
I mean. you're in the middle
of all this stuff and....
Does this ring true to you. Tony?
Yeah. the first time I saw the movie.
I was so shocked by this scene...
because it's exactly...
what the tarmac in Riyadh looked
and sounded and felt like.
And. you know. this massing of troops.
We were the first Marines on the ground...
and we were getting ready to go to war.
It's a really perfect representation of that.
And. by the way.
just to. you know. footnote...
which we could be talking about
on every scene is that...
when Sam directed this. he didn't know
anything about the military. really.
And I think a lot of the movie's...
just amazing qualities...
are his journey of discovery.
his determination...
to get this right and to find out what
really happened and to get it onscreen.
Everything we're talking about
is filtered through Sam's imagination.
And I love this Chris Cooper scene.
This guy is your classic...
Marine officer. who is...
not a buffoon. who's very smart...
and who can talk to the President
as well as he can talk to these guys.
Good afternoon. Marines!
And he's talking to the guys now.
He's putting on his talking-to-guys hat.
For those of you
who don't know me...
I'm Lieutenant Colonel Kazinski.
your battalion commander.
He really looks like a lifer officer.
I mean. he looks like. you know.
a Lt Colonel who's been in for 23 years.
And. again. he's a guy you would trust.
You would follow him.
Those boys have been fighting
since you were nine or ten years old.
These kinds of shots are....
Those are just super authentic shots.
A group of Marines. sitting with their rifles...
being briefed for war...
and shocked here by what they're seeing.
And. again. just so we put this in context...
you know. this is about the first Gulf War...
in which Saddam Hussein invaded
a neighbouring country...
and used these nerve gas...
and. in fact. these troops are part of an
international coalition under UN mandate...
with support of the Arab League.
So they're going to be waiting for months.
they don't know this yet...
to get the diplomacy done...
and to get the troops built up
and to get the alliances built.
But what we want is to go to war tomorrow.
And these guys. like they say on the plane.
"We're going to be back in two weeks. "
'Cause these guys are ready.
You could see how pumped up they were
in the previous scene...
so between that incredible excitement
and anticipation...
of watching Apocalypse Now...
we're now transitioning
into the life of the desert.
You know. our first month in the desert
we were running live patrols...
with ammo locked and loaded...
supposedly ready for the army
to come down. and...
that wasn't going to happen.
We're gonna kick some Iraqi ass!
I love this introduction of Fowler who is. to
me. one of the great characters in the movie.
Because all of these guys
are trained to kill...
because that's what they have to do
as their vocation.
But every now and then you get a guy
that the screw's turned a little too much...
who's not just trained to kill.
but that's what he lives for.
-He loves it too much.
-Yeah. too much.
And his particular psychosis
really becomes detrimental to the unit.
And also. see.
you're starting to meet these guys here...
and you'll see they have
different kind of political viewpoints...
a different kind of everything.
And this is one of my favourite lines
in the movie...
you know. that Troy's gonna say...
after they start talking the politics
in just a second.
You're gonna get all you want
soon enough.
First to fucking fight!
Yeah. For what?
I've been around
these old white fuckers all my life.
They got their fat hands
in Arab oil.
The motherfuckers drink it
like it's beer.
-And it seems kind of funny to--
-He's the subversive.
Yeah. to make the subversive
the guy from Texas. which are like me...
'cause you think that. stereotypically.
he would not be.
But this is just much more real.
And. of course. they dismiss him.
All the rest is bullshit.
This is like the grunt's mantra.
That's what I felt in Vietnam...
even though it was much more
politically charged and this wasn't.
We talked politics every now and then.
but we knew it didn't mean anything.
Right. and. you know. we'd get the papers.
and we knew what was going on...
but. in the end. we were there to fight.
just as Sarsgaard's character just said.
One thing I talk about fairly often
in the book...
something I write about is the
domesticity that the Marine Corps offers.
And it's this simple.
kind of close-to-the-bone living.
And here. I love this scene...
because we see the making of their home.
This is where they're living.
on these cots with these CC mats.
You know.
the guys are pulling out their flags...
and their relics.
Look at her! Ain't she an animal!
You know. it's the interior life
of this family...
that we see emerge onscreen.
We see the making of it onscreen.
Yeah. and also it's just the different ways
they look at their women.
You know. you've got these objects of lust...
and. you know. the girlfriends.
and then you're about to see...
you know. the guy with his wife...
with a completely different idea of beauty.
And. you know.
I really love how different these guys are.
-Give it up!
-Check this out.
-Yeah. boy!
-Give it up. give it up.
No. no. no.
Oh. no! Please don't love me!
The cultural. like.
Mexican versus Cuban stuff was....
You know. there were these two guys
in platoon. one Mexican. one Cuban...
who were always talking trash
back and forth...
about how one or the other spoke Spanish...
and the difference between the women.
And again. here's Troy going to say...
you know. the Marine Corps thing...
if the corps had wanted you to have a wife.
they would have issued you one.
A couple years after I got out
of the Marine Corps...
the General made an order...
that anyone under an E4
couldn't get married...
and he got in a lot of trouble over that one.
You're supposed to be married
to the Marine Corps. if you're at this level.
It's like your calling.
It's almost like being in the priesthood.
Again. these themes of loneliness.
doubt. worry...
about what's happening
to their girlfriends back home...
is introduced right from the beginning.
-You know. I love this.
-Yeah.
'Cause they're just not prepared for it.
They've got the gear...
you know. they've put it on before...
they've used it. they know how to put it on.
Part of the grunt's complaint is...
"I know how to put my gas mask on.
Why are you calling. 'Gas!' again?
"Like. there's no gas. "
Yeah. but then the truth is
that they can't get it on fast enough.
So this is Jamie being. like.
the classic sergeant...
who's not going to let them get soft.
That's your fucking sleeping bag.
you moron! Let's go!
It's been 30 seconds.
What the fuck are you doing?
Get it on!
Bill. I'm wondering if the Marines
that we see on the screen...
and that you first encountered in my book...
if they reminded you of men
that you served with in Vietnam?
Those 18-. 19-year-old guys
that were in my platoon...
you know. they saved my life
over and over. and...
I was a second lieutenant.
which is like the lowest form of life...
and what I quickly learned
was that you just had to...
let your squad leaders
essentially run the platoon...
and just not get in their way.
55 seconds. You're all dead.
And since you're all dead...
I guess you wouldn't mind
taking a little run in these suits.
Let's go!
Swofford. if you don't pick it up...
I'm gonna shoot you
in your fucking foot! Move it!
The price of crude oil
has nearly doubled.
President Bush sends in more troops.
Us. six times a day....
And. again.
this was Sam just pushing to find ways...
to show time passing
and what they're doing.
And we did this. We patrolled in the middle
of nowhere. with no enemy nearby.
And we dehydrate.
You know. I was talking to one of the guys
in the platoon last night. in fact.
And he reminded me
of this three-day patrol we did...
through the middle of the desert.
...into nowhere.
And I love this scene. because
it's what we did. We used our bayonets...
to dig into the earth.
to supposedly look for landmines.
This is also. as Tony said. they were so
anticipating doing what they're trained for.
They fire at nothing.
They throw hand grenades into nowhere.
You will hydrate till I get full.
There you go. Hold it down.
Now. hold them up.
And we look north....
And this. again.
is a great line from Tony's book.
...and we wait for them.
This is our labour.
We wait.
When you're a screenwriter
and you're given a book like Tony's...
what you want to do is just not screw it up.
And this. again. this is sort of added in
from some of the things...
that Tony and the other guys told us.
This is not in the book. I don't think.
-But it was something that happened.
-Yeah.
But when you're given a book like Tony's.
and it's so good...
you just want to get as much of it
as you can into the movie.
I think people will be shocked
by that scene. as well.
Yeah. this is such a great example...
of guys trying to find a way
to stave off the boredom...
and find something to do...
because there are so many times
that you can fire your rifle...
so many times
you can practise land navigation...
so many times you can put your gas mask
on in less than seven seconds.
And. you know. guys literally
went out and found scorpions...
and kept them as pets and had fights.
But I do want to point out that no scorpions
were injured in the making of this movie.
That's good to know.
I just love the way that they're together...
and they love each other
and get on each others' nerves.
They're just trying to pass the time.
What I love about the scene is it's so small.
It's these two little scorpions fighting.
And look how emotionally involved in it
these guys are.
-I know. isn't that great? Yeah.
-It's like the world depended on that...
on that scorpion fight.
Fucking asshole.
Part of what's so great about Tony's book...
is that it captures
what happens to men at war...
in those moments that aren't
the typical Hollywood-combat moments.
But I think that's the heart of this movie.
is what that does to your soul...
to go through this.
This whole sequence here is a wonderful.
sort of. Sam montage about boredom.
You know. you wash your clothes.
you sit around.
This is how I spent nine months of my life.
Yeah. this is the making of the landscape
here. which Bill and Sam just did expertly.
You know. there's a part in the book
where I talk about....
You know. at first we hated the desert.
We couldn't stand it.
And then. eventually.
we realised that the desert was our home...
and the desert was going to be our home
for a while.
That eventually we would fight there.
but first it was going to be our home...
and this scene is the making of that home.
One line we had to cut out
at the last minute...
was a great line from Tony's book.
which was...
you know. "The desert. we thought
we invaded it. but it invaded us. "
...left- versus right-handed
masturbation...
further cleaning of rifle....
Here is. again. this theme of helplessness...
with the one. the most important.
connection you have to the life you knew...
which is your girlfriend or your wife.
And you see it really working on Swoff here.
He doesn't know.
And he sees all these examples...
of what these other women have done
and how they've....
This is a great scene.
again from Tony's book. the Wall of Shame.
Yeah. and. you know.
it's this fear that the guy has...
and some of it may just be unfounded...
but he has no control over
what's going on back in the world.
And later.
in another really important scene...
just before the war starts. we'll hear
Lucas's character talk about that...
about the difference
between the jarheads and the world.
I wonder what she's doing right now.
No way to know.
Now. here are the rules.
This scene came right out of the book.
and there was a time. I think...
though. when we thought
that this would open the movie.
This is one of those scenes
that I just knew...
had to be in the movie.
when I read the book.
Like the watching Apocalypse Now.
And if I get fucked up.
I'm gonna fuck you up.
Take your shirts off.
Show your muscles.
-You've been working out.
-This is censorship.
This whole sequence
where they want to put on a show....
And we did this in Vietnam. too.
We had to....
Of course. you know. it's a little different.
They stayed with this longer.
and we couldn't put on a show that long.
But this is exactly
what he's trying to get them to be...
the Marines that the press office
would like them to be.
And this is a great line from the book again.
You are a Marine.
There's no such thing
as speech that is free.
You must pay
for everything that you say.
"You must pay for everything you say. "
Right. which is true. You end up paying.
And this. again. I think this acting....
This is great.
'Cause the actors
have to be their characters...
not being. you know. being...
-They can't be actors--
-...uncomfortable in front of the....
When. in fact. they are totally comfortable
in front of the camera.
...so I'm proud to serve
my country here.
I have supreme confidence
in all my leaders...
you know. from my team leader....
This is the line that Jamie's character...
you know. wanted Swoff to say.
He wanted them all to say.
"I have supreme confidence. "
He says it perfectly. He gets....
But.... And this guy's just crazy. He's....
And again this was a way to get personal...
just. you know. for each of the characters...
so you could just get a little vignette.
And I wrote some of them...
some of them came from Tony's book.
then he just completely improvised his.
You're a Marine
here in Saudi Arabia.
And this is great. 'cause here's the guy
that didn't want censorship.
And he's just.... You can see what happens.
And these were actually outtakes.
He's just getting ready to do...
his thing he's written. and Sam decided
this was even better. which I think it is.
Do you have nightmares about them?
How do you....
I love it out here.
This is what I want.
And this again. this is the essence
of Peter's character right here.
And so much of the guys that I knew
were like this.
And Troy.
who wanted to be in the Marine Corps...
Ioved the Marine Corps. wanted to be there
more than anything else...
-would've spent his life there.
-That's him.
That's how he lives.
You know. Swoff sort of breaks.
you know. changes the mould here.
He's playing the game at first.
telling her about his--
Because there are two sides here.
And when the Marine says...
that. "I'm confident in our mission.
I'm confident in our abilities"...
and that. "We're gonna go win the war. "
all those things are true.
-But the alternate side...
-Is also true.
...the fear. the loneliness...
the complicated feelings about. "Well.
are we really here for the right reasons?
"Why are we in the desert?
What's going on here?
"Who are we fighting for?"
They're not allowed to voice
those concerns.
Are you scared?
Yes. ma'am.
I'm very happy to be here.
I love my country.
And again. you know.
I just want to say again that these actors...
you know. we could talk about it
anytime in the movie. are extraordinary.
This guy is just....
He has that immigrant enthusiasm
for America. which is all so true...
but when these actors shave their heads...
it was the transformation of them.
just like it is with the recruit.
They became so serious and dedicated...
to getting these characters right
and to honouring...
these characters that they're playing.
the real Marines. I mean...
I think that....
And Jake is. of course. incredible in this.
He doesn't make a false move.
I'm 20 years old...
and I was dumb enough
to sign a contract.
I can hear
their fucking bombs already.
It was great. actually.
when Tony and Jake got to meet...
because the Tony that Jake met
is not the Tony that he's playing.
That's the other interesting thing.
It's the Tony of. you know.
after reading the book. and 10 years later.
But I think he really....
Don't you think he really gets you
the way you were then?
Yeah. he really captures that 20-year-old me.
NBC suits.
That's nuclear-biological-chemical....
People keep asking. "Did Jake study you?
"Did Jake spend a lot of time around you?"
And studying me or spending a lot of time
around me at 34-years-old...
would have been
totally the wrong thing to do.
'Cause it's the 20-year-old me.
it's the young jarhead...
it's the juiced-up. ripped-up kid...
who's on the verge of going to war.
And that's what's so great
about Tony's book. by the way...
is that he is so honest
about how 20-year-old guys think...
and feel and what they do
to be warriors like this.
And a lot of that. as you get to be 30 and 40
and 50. you want to forget.
-Ball.
-Fuck.
Give me the ball.
All right. listen up. guys.
today is your lucky day.
These reporters want to see
how your NBC suits work.
All right. so we're gonna continue
this little football game...
in full chemical gear.
-That's right. Come on. let's go.
-It's 112 degrees.
Then I guess you won't be needing
your parkas. will you?
Let's play!
I'm gonna hurt you. Swoff.
And this is another scene that I just knew...
had to be in the movie...
this playing football in their gas masks.
You know. which....
It's shot as just being shot by the TV guys.
Using his head.
-Jamie's very--
-Yeah.
And. you can see. he's kind of
hamming it up for the reporters.
-Yeah. exactly.
-He's getting his time....
He's getting his 15 minutes.
He's the staff sergeant.
He does that really well.
And it's gonna sink in
on these guys. though...
that so long as those reporters are there...
that they kind of have
a window of opportunity...
because their staff sergeant
really can't come down on them.
-Right. And they can....
-Because....
You know. this is their humiliation of him.
is what we're about to see...
because. you know.
he's always in control of the situation.
He's told them what to tell the reporters.
He's forced them in 112 degrees...
into their mob suits and gas masks
to play football.
And. you know. they're pissed.
-And they're kind of pissed at each other.
-I love this guy.
-Just completely collapses.
-Yeah.
-Who got me? Who got me?
-No. no. I want him.
You want the Mexican leprechaun?
Well. let's take him.
Yeah. I'll take the fucking midget.
I'm the midget?
Let's go. you squishy-faced retard.
And these two guys did this themselves.
This is....
You know. I would love
to take credit for writing this. but--
-That was the two of them.
-Yeah.
And a part of it is the actors. you know.
in the course of doing the movie...
became their characters and lived
on isolation and got the same kind of...
Ioneliness. boredom. connections
that the Marines themselves did.
Yeah. they really captured the essence
of the platoon...
the love-hate relationship
that everyone has with one another.
Here the respect for Jamie.
for the staff sergeant...
but that also we see devolving here.
because things don't work.
My hydration tube is busted.
Staff Sergeant.
And this is so true.
This happened to me in Vietnam. too.
You know. things are all....
You think that everything is gonna work.
and everything is gonna be perfect...
but nothing....
You're always having to improvise.
-Fucking piece of shit!
-I want you to play fucking ball!
And now that. you know. it's like....
It's going to sink in on them that
they actually have the upper hand here...
just so long as those reporters are there.
And this totally aberrant scene.
the field fuck is...
you know. is something that we would do...
and. you know. here Jake yells it.
Field fuck!
Jamie realises what's gonna happen and....
Shit.
He's so good.
He's just.... I mean. he's got this guy down--
And there's like. there's this great line there.
"'Stop it. you assholes. " because...
you know. now that's what they are.
'cause they've got him.
Put your clothes on. assholes!
Come on.
Let's go check out the artillery
and everything.
-Field what?
-He said "field fun."
That's one of the exercises
that we run here in the field.
This is that kind of
strange sexual repression.
You know. it's a very disturbing scene...
because they're frustrated. they're alone...
and they're just pretending
and acting out things.
But they're really trying to stick it to him
and to the desert...
and the interviews.
to all the things they're supposed to say.
Because they're the ones
that are forgotten...
you know. nobody's gonna care about them.
And that's the scene where they're. like.
fucking everyone else...
-and from the book there's a--
-There's a great dialogue...
-and we tried to get it in.
-It's this long...
mantra where.
"Fuck the peaceniks. the politicians...
"you know. everyone else. everyone who's
not a part of our world. because...
"they'll never understand. but mostly
they're not here now. They're not with us. "
That's how it was in the Marines.
is anybody who wasn't out with us...
-we could care less.
-They were lesser than us and....
They didn't understand.
I can't hear you.
This is crazy.
We wanted it to rain in the desert.
We wanted it to be cold in the desert.
'Cause one of the things in Tony's book
is so clear is there's not...
is that you go through seasons there.
And all of them are harsh in their own way.
-Lance Corporal Swofford!
-Yes. Staff Sergeant!
I recently met our corpsman again.
and he reminded me of this night...
that it was freezing cold in the desert...
and we were on this. like.
two-and-a-half. three-day patrol.
And we were so cold that we like
slept together in the same sleeping bag.
I totally forgot about that.
But otherwise. we would've frozen.
You can start
by taking all that down.
Fuck!
Yeah. whatever.
Come on. Swoff. pack up.
Your mummy again. Fergie.
This is. of course. the dog tags
that you're gonna wear when you're dead.
-And...
-They stick it between your teeth.
Yeah. and I spent a little more time on this
in the book...
but. you know. I'd been raised Catholic
and I'd been an altar boy.
And then I came to the Marine Corps.
and for me those two systems...
just weren't gonna work.
They weren't compatible.
And then. you know.
I didn't want Catholicism on my dog tags.
What difference does it make?
God knows you're "no preference."
At least they got
the blood type right.
I mean. which would you rather get?
The wrong prayer or the wrong blood?
One Ionely pink letter
from Sacramento.
Kristina. I wonder what she's up to?
Now. I dare you....
Go jerk off outside.
Here's. again. the payoff of the earlier scene
with the guy with the pregnant wife.
And juxtaposed...
his happiness with his family working out
in his life...
and then juxtaposed
with what's happening to Swoff here.
And you just go the range of emotions
in this scene...
I really think is so true. You know.
you got this guy so proud of his son...
and so happy with his family...
and then here's Swoff. you know.
getting a completely different kind of news.
And. again. it's happening.
you know. inside the tent.
These real. kind of. important scenes
to the emotional life of the platoon...
and all of the Marines
happened inside of that tent.
He's beautiful. man.
I'll put my little boy up.
They see that there's
something troubling Swoff.
And they key in on it.
Part of the reason they key in on it
and give him trouble over it...
is because they want him to get rid of it.
they want him to forget it.
They want to tell him
that it doesn't really matter.
And. see. you have no secrets
from these guys in the 'toon.
You know. everybody knows
what everybody's happening...
with everybody's family life.
with everything else.
You know. you'd heard everybody's stories.
you know everything...
about their girlfriends. what they did
when they were in the eighth grade.
You know so much about each other.
and you can pick up on everything.
I can see it. I can see it now.
She works in a hotel.
She goes into a vacant room. right?
Grabs onto the pole and goes.
"Jody! Jody!"
Then. of course. Fowler. you know.
he always takes things a little too far.
Okay. Corporal.
Hey. Swoff. That's right.
Cheer up. man.
We heading back to the rear.
We'll get some AC...
shit in a flush toilet.
you can use the phone.
-I'm gonna call her.
-You fucking A.
Even if she is fucking someone else.
There's always that. "I'm gonna
help you out. man. I'm on your side. "
And then.
"You know what. but by the way.... "
Root beer shower!
-What? Where are you going?
-To work.
Where you going?
Something that's felt but not articulated
either in dialogue or voiceover here...
is the fact that...
Swoff doesn't really want to leave the tent.
He doesn't want to go back to the AC
and the showers.
He just. you know.... They're in the desert.
and he wants to stay there.
Yeah. and we had the same experience
in Vietnam. too...
you know.
that my son's talked about. as well.
Once you're in the place
where you're supposed to be fighting...
the idea of going back and getting soft...
that is taking showers and having
air-conditioning and sleeping in a real bed...
and. you know. it's just....
You feel like it could kill you.
We're starting to reach this thing
where he's getting so upset and helpless...
about what's happening to his girlfriend...
and then the feelings of jealousy
are really starting to build...
and he can't do anything about it.
But at least he's going to get to call her
on the phone.
And in the bathroom stalls
on either side of him right now...
there are probably other jarheads...
masturbating to pictures of their girlfriends.
And here's the phone call.
the bad connection and all that distance.
How are you?
You can hear that distance. you know.
It's obvious in their miscommunications.
Missing you.
I'm all right. I'm missing you. too.
I saw your mum.
We went to visit your sister.
Well. I got to make one home phone call
from Vietnam. and you had to say. "Over. "
And there was a long gap. but I think this is.
again. just from your book.
Yeah. you know the phone call
was never enough.
You were trying to say too much in too little
time. And this happened. you know.
The girlfriend had a friend
who was a good listener...
who worked with her. nights at the hotel.
How well do you know him. Kris?
Who. Carl?
And the "just a friend" line.
He's just a friend.
How well do you know him?
Oh. God. every time I hear this. it just really
kicks me in the pit of my stomach.
"Tony. he's just a friend. "
-Hello?
-Yeah. I'm here.
And Jake's acting here is just so great.
You see. he's losing everything
that is back home.
-God.
-Kris?
And there are a couple of dream sequences
in the book...
which are much bigger and this is sort of....
We took the idea of it and brought it down
to this one thing about his girlfriend.
As I was reading the book at this part...
you're still feeling for Tony's.
or Swoff's character. so much...
because he's young. and he's in love.
and he's so helpless. and he's in the desert.
And this is sort of. you know.
the symbolism of...
what the desert is doing to him.
And this is. again. a Sam invention of...
here with the mirror. which I think is just...
-amazing.
-Yeah. and I love this scene.
It's so quiet here...
that it's richly disturbing.
This vomiting of the sand is genius.
'Cause the desert is now inside of him.
-It's inside of him--
-I think.... Did he vomit glass in the book...
-or something? I'm trying to remember.
-Yeah.
We wanted to do sand
just 'cause the desert.
'Cause we couldn't get that great line from
the book. like. "The desert invaded us. "
Troy's up there above him smoking coolly.
like. "You said some weird sounds. man. "
And notice how subdued
the barracks here is...
versus the tent out in the desert.
Like this scene where they're actually living.
And then we get. you know.
this is the rec room with the VCR.
Some guy's wife has sent him...
a war movie. The Deer Hunter.
They're gonna watch it.
And. also. see. we wanted to do.... We did
Apocalypse Now with The Valkyries...
and now we're doing The Deer Hunter...
'cause. again. it's that resonance of Vietnam
that got me into the movie in the first place.
And. you know.
and besides Tony's book being so good.
And two very different films. too.
and then here's the home porno...
that is going to change radically
when Dettman realises...
that. you know.
that it's his wife and the neighbour.
And this happened to a guy. I think it
was in Fox Company. in my battalion.
He was still looking on
when this happened?
That's my wife.
That's my fucking wife!
Swoff just sort of notices it.
They're all still into it.
This guy is great in these. you know....
What is this scene. like 90 seconds?
And you know him absolutely.
No! You slut! No!
Fuck!
-You don't need to see this shit.
-Oh. fuck. baby.
You don't need to see this.
Swoff. come on.
And what he says here
is what they're all in part of them feeling...
and he wants to go home.
Fuck! I wanna go home!
Yeah. but again there's that....
These guys. in some way. well. obviously...
they enjoy the pornography.
And. also. the woman's pointing out exactly.
you know. that these infidelities...
-do go both ways.
-Yeah.
Which.... And it's the....
Yeah. you know. they go both ways and....
Obviously. you know.
the guy's been screwing around on her.
It's not just the women
who are unfaithful to the men but....
This was a Jake idea to come up with.
wanting to watch it again.
-And which I think is really brilliant.
-Oh. was it?
-Yeah. it was.
-Yeah.
Yeah. it's a great idea.
And I'd love to take credit for it
as a screenwriter...
but Jake and Sam came up with it.
We had a whole other scene in here
from the book...
of a suicide-attempt scene.
This let us kind of get all the way over
and get to the subsequent scene.
What are you doing?
I'm waiting for you to leave....
I think this is one of the moments where...
as viewers. we see the two men.
you know. coming closer.
You know. Troy is a little older
than Swoff is...
and he's trying to be his guide.
I want to see what it's like...
to watch somebody else
fuck your girlfriend.
He's also. kind of.
the conscience of the movie.
I mean. he's the guy that turns off the VCR.
He's the guy that makes the decisions.
He's the guy that should stay
in the Marine Corps.
-Because you want guys like that in.
-Right.
Come on. Get your shit.
Come on. We're going back.
These desert shots. the sort of....
The machinery at war...
and now they're going back to the desert.
back to the tent.
And this is like Swoff's disintegration.
He's. like. continuing....
He's just trying desperately to hang on
to some shred of his own sanity as....
Through the waiting
and the doubt about his girlfriend.
If wounded. call corpsman.
If dead.
report to graves registration.
If losing his mind. however....
I love this scene.
because there was this guy....
I think he was an S4.
who was selling hooch...
whose mother had sent him brewer's yeast
or something like that...
and he threw in this cheap juice
and let it ferment.
And we should point out that it's because
of the sensibilities of our Muslim allies...
alcoholic beverages were forbidden
in the desert.
They were.
Fly. rumour. on winged feet.
Here...
read this.
And this sort of obscenity
and depravity is great.
"Dear sweet Gloria.
I wish I was up in you now...
"with a finger in your ass.
"Love you. Captain Skinboat."
The Dartmouth kid writing...
-the porno love letters for the Major.
-Yeah.
And it's fun to be able
to get those things in...
just a really quick thing. as you're....
On the fly. kind of.
And this. actually. is....
You know. we had this same guy like this
in Vietnam...
who couldn't figure out
how the claymore went.
Right.
And were there directions right on it?
Yeah. "Front. toward enemy. "
is what he says.
-Got to be a clue.
-Thanks.
And this poor Fergus. the boot guy. is
constantly being assigned people's watch.
And he's kind of the outsider.
-It's Christmas Eve.
-I'll send you out a fucking tree.
Oh. great. a tree. Merry Christmas.
In some ways. for me...
when watching this scene.
I think of our parties.
The private life that we tried to have
inside of our tent...
and this was.... This is it in extremis.
And then. you know. Jake's hats.
the Santa hats. are just like his great touch.
The Santa hat thing is I know a guy
in Vietnam that did exactly this.
That's sort of where the idea came from...
but again it's part of
what Tony kept emphasising...
is this tent was their family.
it was where they were safe.
Where they bonded. they did everything.
you know. they knew each other so well.
And they could tell whose letter it was...
by the smell of the perfume on it.
They got the hooch.
and they were gonna party...
try to get rid of all the things
that are driving them crazy.
And they're alone at Christmas.
You know. this is Christmas.
-And I love the sign on Fowler there.
-Yeah.
Which was in some photos
that I sent to Sam.
-Yeah. You gave me some photos.
-It's not in the book or...
it wasn't in the script.
but I sent Sam a box of--
And Sam saw the photo and he said.
"Oh. yes. "
And it's a....
Yeah. that was the sentiment.
And again. this is great sound editing. too.
To see that. you know...
you get the different song he's listening to.
and compare it to what they are.
Shit.
Oh. shit!
These guys are so desperate for combat.
for action.
And they're really ready for it.
Come on! Now!
I love that Troy is the first guy
out of the tent. too. You know. he's just....
He's the first one that realises what's
going on. and then he's gone. "Okay.
"Okay. Here. we're out of here.
Let's go. we're in it. This is it. "
What the fuck is that?
It's time to do it all!
It's time for me to....
Sorry. guys. I'm really sorry.
It was my sausages.
"It was my sausages. " like...
that could be an answer to so many...
so many mistakes that Marines make.
You know. like.
"Sorry. guys. it was my sausages. "
Fucker's fucked now.
Yeah. I love these stories here.
'cause. again. this goes across every war.
This is some of the classic punishments...
and it's interesting that Swoff is getting
punished for what Fergus did.
Because it was Swoff's responsibility.
it was his watch.
So do you have all
of that unauthorised beverage...
out of your system?
Whose watch was that. Swofford?
-It was mine.
-It was yours.
But since you don't know
how to handle responsibility...
we are demoting you.
I wasn't demoted.
I think I should say for the record.
I know. Tony.
-Bill....
-You were the ideal Marine--
I was meritoriously promoted
upon returning from war.
But I don't think that would've worked
quite so well in the scene. to say...
"Swoff. we're gonna
meritoriously promote you. "
That's true.
I have a screenwriter's licence.
I was able to take the liberty there.
-But you definitely did this.
-I definitely burned the shitters.
-Yeah.
-Which is no fun...
as we can see.
I did this. too.
It's a bad. bad duty.
Hold it right there. Marine.
-The Major's perfect.
-The Major's just perfect.
-He is the classic. self-important officer.
-Yeah.
Stick that back in there.
It's already full
of diesel fuel. sir.
I don't care
if it's full of Chanel No. 5.
I'm not going to the other side
of this camp for my morning glory.
And also. by the way. what you've noticed
here is Dennis did a great job with the set.
As we first saw the bulldozer
just making it. and now it's got....
Every time you see it.
you go back and it's bigger and bigger...
and more things are added and it's homier.
And now we've got these structures
for shitting in.
They really are homier.
The last thing they expected was to make
a home in the desert. They came to fight.
I left you a little gift in there.
Not too hard....
The scene is now getting darker.
Perfect.
Yeah. and this is great acting by Jake.
I mean. you can really see
that he's at the end of his rope.
And he's infuriated
at what's happened to him.
I love the red of the Santa cap in this.
It's just so gleaming.
-Yeah.
-But it's just this disgusting....
And the scene that's coming up
is another one of the scenes...
that when I read the book. I just.
"This has got to be in there. "
It was very hard for me to write about...
because I did something kind of insane.
I lost myself.
He'd gotten me in trouble.
I'd had to burn the shitters because of him.
He was a boot.
He was constantly screwing up.
His mind wasn't on war.
He wanted to listen to his tape from home.
And he fell asleep on fire-watch
and he. you know. failed me.
Failed us.
And I was gonna make him pay here.
I really. you know. I lost it.
My desire for war...
folded into. you know.
my desire to punish him.
He who had gotten me into trouble...
and had sort of. you know.
sacrificed my integrity within the platoon.
And I think. also. is that here you've been....
We've had this love affair with the rifle.
And you've wanted to kill.
and he hasn't been able to...
and so the first thing he does is
he turns it on...
turns the rifle on the guy
that he thinks has betrayed him.
And. again. you listen to the language here.
It starts being all of this
classic Marine Corps training stuff...
describing the rifle. and describing the
sitting position. and we go into the litany.
And. again. this is the payoff
of the Rifleman's Creed...
that we set up in the beginning.
But in a much more horrifying situation.
That's a great point. Bill.
but the language is now...
the mechanical language of nomenclature.
And it's the language of the rifle manual.
And the language of training.
It's not the language of the heart.
It's not the language of the human.
This is what I was supposed to do.
-Jake's acting here is just amazing.
-And Brian. too. I mean. he is so good.
The fierceness of this scene.
-Every time I watch it. I'm kind of shocked.
-This will blow you away.
But it also combines two scenes
in the book.
Which is when he turns the rifle on this...
and there's another scene in the book
where Tony turns the rifle on himself.
And he thinks he's gonna....
Puts the muzzle in his mouth.
Instead of doing two scenes.
which in a sense...
were variations of the same kind of thing.
we combined them into this one.
But this one is mine.
Without my rifle. I am nothing.
Say it. you fucking idiot!
-No.
-This is my rifle!
There are many like it.
but this one is mine!
Without my rifle. I am nothing.
When I read your book...
and John Gregory Dunne
sent me an e-mail...
he'd written a review
in The New York Review of Books...
and said. "This is an amazing book. "
'Cause we had this conversation for 30 years
about the military experience in America.
And I read the book. and I just had to do it.
And Doug and Lucy Fisher called and said.
"Would you be interested?"
I just said. "Yes!" And they asked.
"Did you want to fly out and talk?"
"No. I just want to do it. "
Because the thing Tony did in his book
was capture so powerfully...
and so honestly. the passage
that a young man goes through...
from being a civilian. to being a Marine.
to back again. You don't see that.
People don't get inside and let you see
the things as honestly as Tony said. and...
I just thought it was an extraordinary thing.
And Tony's experience in the book
is so clearly done and so concrete...
that my basic job as a screenwriter
was not to mess it up.
The better the book the harder it is
to adapt into a screenplay.
You would fracture time and be in the war
and before the war and after the war.
And I sort of did the first draft
of the screenplay...
with. you know. first act before the war.
second act during the war...
and a third act after the war.
And Sam kept saying. "Look.
I really think the heart of this movie is...
"the war stuff. the whole Marine stuff. "
We had to find ways to do the before-the-
war material and the after-the-war material...
just so cinematically.
and stay to the heart of that movie.
And Sam just had this vision
from the beginning of what he wanted to do.
And we would be on the phone from the set.
You know. I was coming to New York
for the editing.
Because he just was so determined to keep
making it as good as it could possibly be.
You know. and never being satisfied
right up to the end.
And we were writing. tweaking the voiceover
three or four weeks...
before the movie came out.
You know. and it's really been
an extraordinary collaborative experience...
and I think the actors would say
much the same thing...
that they all felt like if they were gonna
have to be in a foxhole with the director...
this was the guy
they'd wanna be in a foxhole with.
Working with Tony on this
has been a real joy for me. too...
because I feel. you know. like a...
almost an ancestor to him as a Marine.
You know. from the previous war
and all the Vietnam echoes.
And just wanted so badly. and Sam did. too.
to really be true to his book...
and to have Tony be proud of what we did.
that we didn't mess up too bad.
Troy. Troy.
Who are they. man?
One of the things that makes Troy. again.
so interesting a Marine here is that...
he's not trying to act like
he knows what he's doing when he doesn't.
You know. and that's what you want
your team leader to do.
This was kind of fun.
-Yeah. this is a great--
-Let them speak in Spanish.
The dialogue between the two guys.
He raises his right hand.
He's like. "Yeah. man. That's how you do it. "
And this was. again. part of the book
that was really fascinating to me is that...
you do have these
almost bizarre experiences...
wandering in and out of the desert.
-Bedouins appearing--
-These Bedouins just appeared.
We didn't know who they were.
I mean. there's a very real way
in which we wanted them to be...
Iraqi Republican Guard.
What do we do now?
And we wanted these guys to be the enemy.
We wanted them to be
the Republican Guard.
You know. we wanted to engage.
This was going to be our first moment of
combat. and we were gonna wipe them out.
See those guys pulling their rifles.
they're ready to shoot.
You got to think.
this is so true of what's going on now...
and what happened in Vietnam.
what happened in World War II is that...
you just get in these situations where
you either pull the trigger or you don't.
And sometimes
you don't have time to decide.
It's so symbolic to me of the situations...
that these kids
or these guys get into where...
you ask a young man to go off to war
and either kill or die for his country.
You know. you really are asking
the most profound thing...
you can ask a human being to do
for his society.
And so this passage
they're going through here...
the deciding not to shoot...
is as important. you know.
as deciding to shoot.
In fact. more so in this case. because
these Bedouin are completely innocent.
And it would have been easy for us
to simply engage them.
That means kill them.
-Kill them.
-That's the euphemism.
In the case of the movie.
it's an important moment...
because Swoff
has just done something reprehensible...
and understandable...
but really so complexly difficult.
And now he's actually
done something good.
If he hadn't done that. who knows
what would have happened at that moment.
This is their. really. first and only...
interaction with any nationals.
You know. it's this moment
where he's human.
Swoff spoke Arabic.
Sounded like a duck....
And then here we find out
that it was Fowler who shot the camels.
...at least we finally saw something.
You guys should see
what the .40 does...
to the head
of a fucking camel. though.
Although that line is just like....
You know. that's what they want.
They want a head shot. so he took it.
It turns the head inside out
in about three fucking knots.
The head shot's
like a motherfucker. too.
It's easy shots. slow....
And. you know.
this is totally obscene and distasteful.
Wow! Here they are! My lady love!
Show's starting. boys!
Hey. teach me some of that Arabic.
What's. "Come suck my dick"?
...ducks fucking....
Fowler is pushing the envelope.
But he's as real as all the other guys.
I mean. you can see their reaction to him.
Yeah. look at them. they're looking like.
"What's wrong with you?
"What's wrong with you. man?"
-She'll never forget me. man.
-It's not funny. man.
That bitch wanted me.
Did you see that?
-You truly are an asshole.
-Come on. man.
You just haven't got
to kill anything yet.
Yeah. see. but what Fowler says here.
though. it has such an element of truth in it.
You know. it almost. like.
explains the scene with Fergus right there.
Listen up!
I'm about to read to you
what Mr Saddam Hussein...
has just said to the Iraqi people.
And you better not consider this
a bunch of bullshit.
Now we see movement. right?
We see the trucks moving.
The camp has been static.
And it's not static anymore.
"Kuwait is the branch
that must be returned to the tree.
"The blood of the infidels
will flow like a river.
"Jihad is the way
of all Arab people."
We are now Operation Desert Storm.
And we're the fucking
righteous hammer of God.
And that hammer is coming down.
It's real now.
We're going to the border.
And that's what they've been waiting for.
They've been waiting
to make it to the border.
They've been waiting for the fight.
And there it is.
I mean. again. you suddenly sort of see
this huge mechanism of war...
and. you know.
there's 575.000 troops. there.
And you compare it to the size
of the troop strength we have in Iraq now...
I mean.
it is an awesomely huge military operation.
-Of which our guys are a small part.
-Yeah.
It's mammoth.
And this pill scene again. is another thing
I thought should really be in the movie...
because it's....
It's very scary. you know.
They don't know what's gonna happen.
They are really scared.
And the story is. like.
you don't know what these pills are.
And. you know.
now there's controversy over them.
Some people believe that...
veterans who are suffering
from Gulf War Syndrome...
that these pyridostigmine bromide pills...
might have something to do with it.
And of course. we don't know it then...
but it's something else that. you know.
we're just being told to do.
Like. "Do this and the reason you should
do this is because it might save your life. "
And this is classic Kruger. too.
He's just not gonna take anything.
I'll take the fucking pills.
and a year later...
my asshole will turn inside out
and start fucking talking to me.
-It's all a bitch.
-These pills ain't worth a shit.
Kruger. you country motherfuck!
In 1987. Saddam Insane
used chemical weapons...
against the Kurds. and he killed
thousands like fucking that.
The ones that lived.
their kids came out fucked up.
Eight toes to one foot.
no anal opening...
retarded. blind.
Such fucked up
little motherfuckers...
they should have
just killed them all anyway.
None of the Marines that I served with...
have claimed to suffer
from Gulf War Syndrome.
-But a lot of people have.
Just like. with Agent Orange in Vietnam.
it took a while. And it's still controversial.
And I think some Veterans are not receiving
what they should be receiving.
Well. even now they're doing
the anthrax vaccines.
There are a lot of people not sure
they should do that.
It's a context of this modern war where
you have biological and chemical weapons.
And you try to do the antidotes.
and they're not sure if they're even....
-This is classic Kruger here. you know.
-Right.
"Yes. Staff Sergeant. " and he spits it out.
Although Kruger was smart enough
to spit it out--
And don't you have memories of just
digging sand. Tony. you know. my God....
You're just digging for days. moving from....
You know. sometimes
we would move three times in a day...
and dig fighting holes.
Fucking zoomies.
You know. this is a great moment because...
you know. Troy vocalizes...
probably what some of them are feeling.
and that is that...
"This war is going on over our heads.
It's been going on for a month.
"They're dropping bombs.
We shoot from 1.000 yards.
"And then the war is moving
at a mile a minute. "
To go that far in Vietnam.
that would take a week.
In World War I. a year.
This is one of the things that was different
about this war from mine...
and from the war today. actually...
which is. this was very much
a war with a clear mission...
with massive air power.
And the actual guys on the ground...
who had this idea of what was
gonna happen when they went...
are finding the war has changed
underneath them.
And. of course. it's the Troy character
who is the truth teller here...
and it's not what they want to hear...
but he's saying it.
for reasons which they don't know yet.
Swofford. you got to sign
your waiver again.
I can't read
your fucking handwriting.
Yes. Staff Sergeant.
-This is an important moment.
-Notice he always grabs his rifle. I love this.
They got the Jim Deever arm.
They do everything. I mean...
It's really so.
you never go anywhere without it.
You never go anywhere without your rifle.
-Even if it's just to go--
-He grabs it...
just to go talk to the Staff Sergeant.
And this is a great moment. I think...
you know. the Staff Sergeant...
as much as he punished Swoff in the past.
sort of...
understands the bond
between Troy and Swoff and the platoon.
And Troy's link to the Marine Corps...
the importance of the Marine Corps
to him in his life...
and he wants to make sure
that Swoff is gonna look out for Troy.
So when we get back home. he's out.
And that. I think. is the other side
of these guys. like Sergeant Sykes says...
is that they really become
almost the father of their....
They do take care of their guys.
And this is very real. My guys did that. too.
You know. they were always aware
of the problems the kids were having...
and what to do with them
and how to help them out.
Because a Marine
who's not thinking about his job...
but is thinking about things
he's worried about back home...
is somebody that can get himself
or someone else killed.
And here. you know. Swoff is angry at Troy.
because he wasn't going to tell him...
that he's going to be kicked out.
And Troy has this sort of hands-off attitude.
-What?
-So you weren't even gonna tell me?
What?
Why don't you just shut the fuck up
and mind your own business?
One of the things you look at
as you see this berm. is that's the border.
And it's very clear what they have to do.
They have to go and get Saddam Hussein's
troops out of Kuwait where they invaded.
It is a clear mission.
And. unlike in Vietnam
where the mission became very confused...
or even today where it's quite confused...
this was a war in which.
with the Powell Doctrine...
you had a clear mission.
you had overwhelming force...
and they had a clear exit strategy.
And that was supposedly that they'd learned
the lessons from Vietnam for this war.
And now. of course.
you know. my son's war...
you know. is disturbingly. for me.
more and more like Vietnam...
and less and less like this.
-Nobody gives a rat's ass.
-No. we're jarheads.
Yeah. what the fuck do you know?
This is really important...
when Lucas's character just said.
you know. "We're jarheads. Swoff.
"The world doesn't stop
just because we're at war. "
That's their greatest fear.
They want the world to stop. but it doesn't.
And they know that the world continues.
That people keep living their lives
while they're at war.
This is the last scene inside a tent.
you know. where they really are....
Killed 37 Chinese by hand
during the Boxer Rebellion of 1900.
-The greatest weapon on earth?
-The Marine and his rifle!
They're giving Troy the initiation that he had
supervised Swoff getting at the beginning.
But this time. he's actually getting it.
Get him down!
They all know
that he's gonna get kicked out.
And they all know that he wanted to be
a Marine. nothing more...
-and so this is their--
-He has to be marked.
This is their gift to him.
As far as they're concerned.
that's what he is.
And they're saying. you know.
"This is what you'll always be. "
And this is incredible acting
by Peter Sarsgaard here.
You see the pain...
but also the kind of joy of it
or the acceptance of it.
These guys bonding with themselves
just as they're about to go into battle.
And the voiceover here...
from Tony's book. I think. is just perfect.
...inside of our circus.
we cannot be touched.
The circus atmosphere. you know.
was our safety.
-The tent was our safety.
-Yeah.
...to believe this.
Incoming!
Corpsman!
This is actually really greatly shot...
because. the truth is.
is when you're in these situations like this...
sometimes sound goes away. or vision.
You're overwhelmed. one sense or another.
You do have a guy like Swoff...
that just kind of zones out
of whatever is happening around.
Yeah. this is what I've been waiting for.
and now here it is.
Finally.
And it echoes. you know.
the soon to come oil-well fire scene.
Most men of every generation...
going back to the time of Homer.
have always wondered...
what they would do
if they were faced with a situation like this...
if they had to go into combat. if they had to
find out what they were made of.
And this. of course. is your nightmare.
-That you're gonna piss your pants.
-Which most of us do...
one time or another.
-Troy. get on that radio.
-Radio's dead.
I was sent off to the com shack
to get batteries during this scene...
and it was obviously one of the...
more anxiety-provoking moments
of the war for me.
The first time we were fired at.
and then you're being sent on a mission.
And artillery coming in
is so terrifying. because it's so random.
And you just know
there's no place you feel safe.
And when you have to be out in the open
with rounds coming in...
I mean. this is as terrifying as it gets.
And there's the. you know.
occasional call for corpsmen....
Yeah. these guys are in their holes.
There's no one coming over the berm.
There's no one fighting.
There's no one.... You know.
what they're ready for is to fight with rifles.
And there's no one to fight with their rifles.
We need batteries for the 77.
-Fuck!
-Man. we are fucking dying!
And these knuckleheads
give him a dead battery.
You know. the com guys.
like. you hate the com guys...
because they're always screwing up.
and of course they give him a dead battery.
-What took you so long?
-Fuck you.
Here are the coordinates.
call that fucker in.
And. by the way. these equipment things.
they're so real for Tony's war...
but they were real for us in Vietnam...
and they're real for the guys
that are out there today.
I mean. today being 2005...
I'm hoping that years from now
it will be different. but....
Sykes says we're going after them!
We're gonna get some!
And now. this is. "We're gonna get some. "
Which is the call to war.
And then they've breached through the berm
and now they've crossed the border.
And they're into Kuwait.
And this is exactly as you move
across the border....
You know.
something that's not in the film is the fact...
that my sniper partner and I were.
for a few days. running missions...
across the border
and watching where the Iraqis were.
They were moving back and forth
across the minefield in these safe passages.
We marked those on the maps
and moved really quickly.
There was first a battle plan...
that gave 36 to 48 hours. I believe.
to breach these minefields.
And whole battalions of men
were through these minefields...
in six hours.
The ground war. as well. was ahead of itself.
Let's drop
that righteous hand of God!
This is this horrifying friendly-fire scene.
which is planes here...
but in the case of my platoon
it was tanks from a nearby unit...
that misidentified the convoy
that was right behind us as being enemy.
My scout team leader got on the radio
and got the attack stopped...
but not before our own tanks
had hit us a couple of times.
Incoming!
This is so terrifying.
You see the looks on their faces...
when they suddenly realise that
these planes. which they think are allies...
are turning around
and going to attack on them.
This happens in every war. It's confusing.
Things don't happen as you expect.
Quebec 4 Delta.
this is Echo 5 Charlie.
Request medevac. priority.
Marines down. in grid 671584.
We'll mark with smoke. over.
And I really love
the Jamie Foxx response here...
which is whatever's happening behind them.
their mission is ahead. you don't stop.
Fowler can't believe it...
like. these guys who were supposed
to be killing the enemy...
just turned on them.
Keep moving.
They could be over this next berm.
And this was that highway of death.
which is. I mean...
of all the war images I've ever seen...
is got to be one of the most disturbing.
It's almost like....
It reminds me of those pictures...
of the Gls walking into Buchenwald
or something in World War II.
Where you just see this...
suddenly you're confronted with horrors
that you could not have imagined.
This is all the results of the air war.
Without that six-week air war...
we would have been engaging the enemy...
fighting position to fighting position.
-We would've had a lot more casualties.
-Rifle combat.
Yeah. we would've lost more guys.
So that six weeks of air war
that frustrated us...
and continued our way...
we realised later saved many of our lives.
I love the quiet of this scene.
Their movement through this waste.
They don't have any idea.
I mean. it's just suddenly hitting them.
Throughout the desert. you know.
the defensive positions...
and also in the major throughways
that had had a lot of convoys...
you know. had scenes like this.
where there was a lot of devastation.
And also. you know.
out in the middle of the desert...
I remember artillery guns
just twisted like pretzels.
Tanks with their turrets blown off.
upside down.
Bodies inside of them. Bodies in the desert.
-What are you doing?
-They were trying to get away.
Fuck it. man. Come on.
This is one of those difficult issues of war.
Like dropping the atomic bomb
in Hiroshima. you know...
where you see the horrors
of the aerial destruction.
On the other hand...
a lot of these guys right here might not
still be alive if this hadn't happened.
So. you know. it raises lots of questions.
You know. there's an integrity
about these guys...
that fight on the ground
and engage the enemy personally.
The people that drop bombs from the air.
it's just a different thing.
You're not.... You're doing it....
It's more mechanical.
It's like. it's not as....
I don't know. it's very complicated.
And this is a great scene
where they have to eat.
Fergus. here.
Thanks.
And. you know. one of the things about this
is the juxtaposition of just...
the daily routines of maintaining your life.
like just eating your lunch...
with what they'd just seen.
I think that's part of the...
what's on the other side
of being in the Marines or being in war...
that is so hard to explain to civilians.
And I think this movie...
and Tony's book. particularly.
really does a great job of doing...
which is that you're put in situations...
you simply could not
possibly have imagined.
This is one. too.
with this circle of guys that looked...
so much like the guys that he just left alive.
his friends.
Kind of the Iraqi equivalent.
And. Tony. why don't....
You should talk about this.
'Cause this is one of the moving moments
in the book. I think.
Yeah. this was literally the scene
on the other side of that destruction...
where the rest of the platoon was eating...
and I walked....
I walked on to the side of it
and came upon this scene.
I was compelled to sit down.
Sit down at this circle of death.
In the book there's more interiority.
But I think it's captured here
quite expertly with....
You know. I vomited.
I tasted the smell of death.
I have the taste of pears. dehydrated pears...
and chocolate in my mouth from my MRE.
And then just the taste of this death
was in my mouth.
Jake looks so defeated here and so small.
He's burdened by his gear...
and by. you know.
all this death that surrounds him.
In the book I talk about feeling
as though I'll never again be so alive.
And. you know. the interesting thing
about filming this and doing the movie...
was that there's a great voiceover
that goes with that...
but it was too specific.
You know. it was better. I think.
to let the viewer's imagination just go.
And I love the line he says here that.
"What's over there?"
It's like he just says "nothing"
because it's beyond words.
There's no language.
there's no words in the language...
to describe what he saw.
And Sykes knows that he saw something.
but he's not gonna. like. push him.
And that's another one of those moments.
I think...
for me watching the film.
where there's another connection...
between the lifer
and the guy who's gonna get out...
an understanding.
Yeah. I think Sykes. you know.
immediately picked up on something...
with Swoff there.
Then there's this amazing curtain-raiser
on the next part of the movie...
where the oil fields are lit.
and they don't know what it is at first.
Yeah. This is exactly how we experienced
the oil-well fires. We....
You know. they started. the sky got dark.
And then this little.... At first.
these little pinpricks of oil started falling.
And I opened my mouth like that.
I looked up.
I watched this scene.
and it's exactly as I experienced it.
That rain on his face. it's amazing.
Yeah. "The earth is bleeding. "
That was.... Just the idea of that is...
again. part of what makes this experience
so eerie.
And so different
and so specific to Tony's war.
Shit.
This is. like. rain on top of the oil-well fires.
My eyes is burning! Shit!
Oh. fuck! Fuck. it's in my eye.
I can't see.
Oh. shit. it's burning!
It's burning!
This is the guy from Texas. too.
Yeah. this is the guy
that's always talking about oil.
Don't rub your eyes.
Shit. it's burning!
Hey. just close your eyes.
The Giant scene that he. you know.
references is all about...
the beauty of oil.
and what it can do to you...
and. you know.
how it transforms your life for the better.
And then here you have this.
which is just a form of hell for them.
This is as close to it as it gets.
the fires. the oil. the blackness.
Hey. listen up!
The wind's changed.
We're moving out this shit.
Let's move!
I came here to fight.
I've just got to get out
of this fucking oil.
This is completely specific to Tony's war.
This burning fire. blackness. darkness.
You know. it's just. "Oh. my God!"
And I love this shot of Sykes.
'Cause he's seen a lot.
but he's never seen this.
You know. he's alternately shocked
and excited by it.
That's Vietnam music. man.
Can't we get our own fucking music?
Yeah. "That's Vietnam music. man. "
There were these Psy-Ops...
helicopters were playing
all of the music of Vietnam.
...what's Fowler doing
digging way over there?
He ain't digging.
And this is a hugely disturbing scene.
You know. a guy in the platoon
was desecrating corpses...
and I confronted him about it.
Nothing.
Our orders are to dig over here.
In the book. I spent a lot of time later
thinking about him...
and his need to do this.
It's sick. and Fowler has lost something.
He's like on the other side.
But he's trying to find. in a way...
in a really disturbing way.
he's trying to find meaning.
He's trying to make some kind of sense
of this crazy situation that he's in.
And by the way.
this goes back to Homer and The Iliad...
when they drag Hector's body
around the gates of Troy.
And it's true of every war.
It is one of the most disturbing things
about it. is that there is this feeling...
when you've gone through this.
and there's death around you...
that you are alive and they are not...
and there's something
so powerful about that.
And disturbing.
This is one of the most disturbing things.
And Fowler is not apologetic at all.
You don't like Ahab?
This is war. man.
Now he's defiant.
This is war. You can't handle it?
What are you. a fag?
If you fucking touch me.
I will beat your fucking head in.
I swear to God.
Get it out of here.
The whole goddamn desert
is shitting dead ragheads.
Have we done anything?
Have we done anything
but walk around in the sand?
I didn't kill him. He's dead.
Move.
Fuck you.
There's tons of crispy critters
around here. man.
And this crispy critters phrase.
that's a Vietnam phrase. right?
Yeah. it's a Vietnam phrase. Yeah.
'Cause didn't Sam ask you.
like. what'd you call the corpses?
Yeah. I said. "crispy critters. "
Yeah. it's a way
of trying to handle with language...
what is incomprehensible
at some level of your soul.
You're just.... This is the stuff...
that is beyond
most civilian understanding is...
how do you cope with this?
And you see different ways
in which they are.
Fowler is an aberration in the platoon.
but he's also part of a tradition.
Not necessarily a proud tradition...
but just a fact of war
that goes back thousands of years.
The living. and what they do to the dead.
This scene. I don't think....
Is this in your book. Tony?
-No. it isn't. You--
-It came out of something we talked....
Sam really fell in love with this...
and I think it's just this eerily.
amazing moment...
where you see a sensitivity
to the Swoff character...
-that you just never saw before. and it's--
-And it's beautiful.
I had forgotten that it was in the script...
and the first time I saw the movie
I was surprised by it.
Was it in one of the photos we saw?
We saw a picture of a horse.
I think it was possibly
in one of those photos. yeah.
And then Sam and I were talking about it.
And just in the midst of all this horror...
you know. there is a moment where
he connects with this helpless animal...
which is covered with oil.
And it's really.
probably. not going to be okay.
Here. Swoff is trying to gain
some kind of humanity.
He's burying this corpse
that someone else was willing to desecrate.
And there are lots of other corpses
that aren't getting buried...
but he's gonna bury it.
You know. it's like you can do one thing.
And this was a scene we sort of put in.
you know. to give the Sykes character...
a real. kind of. moment...
where he not only is coming out
to check on Swoff...
but is essentially giving his credo.
what he believes in about the Marine Corps.
At the end of this there's...
you know. I think. the important line that
I remember hearing a lot of the lifers say...
"Where else are you going to see
stuff like this?
"Who else gets to see this?
"Who else gets to live this way? Nobody. "
That's why he doesn't go back to Compton
and make $200.000 a year...
-and get a new Dodge truck.
-Right.
Because he's not going to see this
anywhere else.
Though we've talked about this before.
that regardless of the horror...
and alternate joys and exhilaration...
that a lot of men. you know.
who fought in World War II...
or Korea or Vietnam or...
you know. who've been in combat anywhere
will talk about the period at war as being...
some of the best years that they lived...
some of the best moments of their lives.
And that they'll never live as cleanly...
or at such a high plane
of confidence and ability.
Yeah. exactly.
And. I think. you know.
you see a spectrum of human behaviour...
in civilian life.
but in war it's stretched way out...
both in the good and bad directions.
And you see the people that are willing
to give you their last drop of water...
or even give their lives for you
in a way that you never see in civilian lives.
And you see horrors as well. but....
This guy. again.
it's this gap between the lifer...
and the guy that's just in for the.
you know. the four years.
And the lifer. Jamie. is trying to tell Swoff...
'cause he sees that Swoff
could be a good career Marine...
if he really decided to stay in.
"Do you get it?"
You know what I'm saying?
-There's that great look on Jake's face.
-Really.
And that's what they're seeing. you know.
This really captures
that disturbing ambivalence about war.
Is that it is so terrible.
and yet men are so drawn to it.
And for some of them.
it's the best thing they ever did.
Even though they buried the horrors and
the things they saw and who they were...
a few things that are left are those moments
of decency or humanity...
that you try to grab out of the terror of it all.
...most definitely hard core.
And meaning. because every day
there was some kind of mission...
no matter how small.
And this is their mission.
This is their mission. now.
They've been told. you know...
"We're attaching you to the Colonel.
"He wants my best sniper team.
you guys are it. "
Fucking A.
Get a kill. you fucking pussies.
This is another one of those scenes
that just looks and sounds...
and feels exactly like the desert did.
You know. we were on our way up
toward an airfield in southern Kuwait...
that hadn't yet been taken.
You know. and just bringing the stuff to
the screen with such an incredible realism...
I think is an achievement
of all the sort of technical guys...
and Sam and everybody else.
And I love the way that the footsteps
are white on the dark. black earth.
-Sykes thinks you boys are good.
-Yes. sir.
Well. if it comes from him
it's not bullshit.
And this is. you know.
this is the Colonel giving them the mission.
The thing that they've been waiting for.
And he does it in a way
that challenges them. as well.
...003.
The recon reports two
high-ranking officers....
So here they're receiving their mission
from the Colonel.
And. you know. their mission is to be the
eyes and ears of the battalion commander.
They're being asked to do the thing
that they've wanted to do for months now...
and for years even.
Aye-aye. sir.
This is not Rambo time.
He's very clear that the air power
that's supposedly winning the war...
is not available to him right now.
So if they can get these soldiers
in the tower...
the whole battalion is not going to have
to attack these Republican Guard...
and take all these casualties.
So it's a real mission.
If they can do it.
then they can save a lot of American lives.
-And he's going to challenge them. too.
-Right.
And that. you know. was one of the knocks
against the sniper platoons...
because. you know. we had our better rifle.
Yeah. the regular Marines
always resent you guys.
Always.
Yeah. so why did they resent you guys.
Tony?
Well. 'cause. you know.
we were shooting from 1.000 yards and....
-You got good gear.
-We got good gear.
You have less discipline.
They were humping up a hill.
and we were in helicopters.
You know. we did our own PT.
physical training.
And weren't your units a little less
rigidly organised compared to....
Yeah. You know.
we could go first-name basis...
and. you know.
there was a chief scout in every team.
You know.
there was a shooter and a spotter.
And. also. you worked alone
with just these two guys...
as opposed to being to part of a unit...
which just means you had to be able
to function just by yourselves.
Yeah. and we had a lot of autonomy
that way.
And so. you know. the grunt who's
in a platoon of 16 guys doesn't like that.
And now they're looking for the shot.
And. by the way. the hardest thing
out in combat is to be by yourself.
And these guys. to be out....
I mean. I can't even imagine being out
with just two guys like this...
you know. 'cause I was always in a platoon
with a bunch of other guys.
The sun's going down. Shit!
Wait.
Thank you. Jesus.
Romeo. Golf. Charlie.
This is Lima 2 Sierra. Over.
I love the line here.
This is what Sam wanted them to say is....
That's what they look like. huh?
The first time he saw me. he said
he wanted something like. you know...
-a realisation that this is--
-This is the guy I've been looking for.
These are the.... A human face on the enemy
we've been looking for so long.
For them. they're finally alone.
They're finally in that tower alone
with the shot.
We see him. you know. calling the distance.
calling the wind.
Swoff's behind the rifle.
Troy's calling the wind.
And then this incredibly disturbing thing
right now...
is that I really want them to take the shot.
You know.
I really have gotten into their world...
and I feel like.... And I'm thinking.
"Why do I want them to do this?"
You know. but I do.
And I think. yeah.
the film makes the viewer...
want what the two Marines
in this tower want.
That should be kind of disturbing
and shocking for the viewer.
Permission to fire.
"Permission to fire. "
You see how he is?
His handset was just shaking there
when he got the news a little bit.
He was so.... Couldn't believe it.
And that. and again. we're seeing
the life through the rifle which is...
every time that happens. it's exactly
as the sniper behind the rifle sees it.
That's the world of the sniper.
And. here. their shot is ruined.
We got air. I'm calling it in.
We have permission to take the shot.
You know. this is the lifer Major who
comes in. and. you know. the college guy...
bad knees from college football.
Bad knees. College football.
And right now. they're being respectful.
they're trying to argue with him...
but this guy is going to degenerate
pretty fast.
...how many chances
you're gonna get to do this.
Wait. wait. wait.
We have to remember that Troy's gonna be...
kicked out of the Marine Corps
when he gets home.
Those aren't my orders. Marine.
Hitman 45--
No. wait. wait. wait.
-Hitman 45--
-Wait. wait. wait.
Wait. sir. we won't tell anybody.
We don't need to tell anybody.
You know. I was the guy behind the rifle
with my reticle on the enemy's head...
and it was denied me. and I was angry.
It was this thing that I'd been after
for many years.
Hitman 45.
This is Bravo 4--
For many years
after leaving the Marine Corps...
you know. in some dark moments.
I wanted to go back.
I wanted to have a chance to kill again.
And. you know. we wrote this thing so that
there would be a true confrontation there.
And I think part of the reason was.
is it felt right...
but also because so much of Tony's book
is about coming to terms...
with not getting to take the shot.
Tony. talk about how you were saying that...
what Peter's character is going through here
mirrored your experience after that.
Yeah. this is a great compression
of really many years of experience for me...
and a real long investigation in the book
about that desire that I had...
to have gone back
and to have taken that shot.
And to even consider
returning to the Marine Corps...
-to go back to war.
-And how you didn't feel....
You didn't feel like a real. true Marine.
'cause you didn't get to--
Because I hadn't killed.
Like. we had been shot at by rockets
and artillery...
but that didn't matter.
because I hadn't pulled the trigger this time.
Oh. man.
It really wasn't until writing Jarhead
that I realised that...
in taking those kills from me that this
officer had actually given me something...
that I would have been altered even more...
had I pulled the trigger.
Hitman 45. Hitman 45.
This is Bravo 4 Lima. Over.
And now. you know.
the Major's called in the air and....
You know. the thing that the snipers
wanted to do. the one shot...
to possibly make the whole unit surrender...
has been taken from them.
The loss of that shot reverberated with me
for many years...
and it was part of our discussion
when we came back as a unit...
trying to figure out....
We had combat-action ribbons.
Did we even rate them.
because we hadn't killed?
Had we seen enough war?
You see. this is the uniqueness of this war
and how short it was...
and how unlike
what they had expected it was.
And Tony and I have talked about.
you know. why we joined the Marines...
I mean. I was drafted. and I think
one of the things that's so interesting...
and I didn't have any choice...
but it turned out to be
one the best things I ever did.
But I think Tony's book.
in some ways this movie is really about...
why he did it and what it meant to him.
One reason I started writing Jarhead
was to...
you know. I was 30 years old.
and I was a writer...
and I really didn't really understand
this 20-year-old version of me...
that Jake has just portrayed.
And. you know.
it took me the writing of the book...
to kind of understand him.
understand his savagery...
the violence. the way he lived.
understand that it was complicated.
And that it was complicated for others.
as well. and not just me.
It was kind of. in some ways.
an apologia for the person I'd been...
but. also. I think the film is the same thing.
A love letter to the other men I served with...
and the men and women
who serve anywhere...
because it's an understanding
of the rigorous life...
and the long-term complications
that can result from it.
That's absolutely why I wanted to do it. too.
Was just because I wanted to say something
to the guys I served with in Vietnam...
and to my son's guys in Iraq now.
and to Tony's guys...
you know. to be a part of helping
bring Tony's story to the screen.
Motherfuck. it's gotten
the battalion.
Because right now.
these guys are so scared.
They're on their own.
They think their battalion's being attacked.
To be just with two guys
in the middle of the desert...
I mean.
this is an absolutely terrifying moment.
I remember being so scared like this.
You know. you just think...
"You go up that hill and you're going to die.
but you've got to do it. "
We thought that
we were going to engage the enemy...
now we were going to get our kills.
And we were greeted
with an entirely differently scene.
Which was a V-day party.
I love the burning. the barrel on fire.
plus the oil-field fire.
You know.
it's like this is their bonfire to celebrate.
Right. Like. we'll make our own fire.
I love this. their footsteps in the sand.
They're coming down that great dune.
And everybody else is just shirts off.
and they still have their....
And they still don't even know
what's going on right now.
You didn't get the memo. did you?
Having a little party.
You're a little overdressed.
This shit is over. motherfucker.
You didn't die.
Have a cigar.
It won't kill you.
I just remember. you know.
first my confusion...
and just that exhilaration
that everyone was feeling.
Like. "It's over. guys. we're going home.
You're gonna go home to your girlfriend. "
Did you get a fucking kill. man?
And this. too. like.
"Did you guys kill? Did you take that shot?"
And. also. they all think that they're done.
For these guys. the desert is over.
they think. in their head.
And. you know. again.
I think it's just sinking in on them that...
here's a guy that's trained...
and wanted nothing more than
to fire his rifle in war. and the war is over.
And he never got to fire his rifle.
He went to war and never fired his rifle.
I never shot my rifle.
You do it now.
See. I think that's one of the things
that's interesting about this war...
is that. you know. in World War II...
a lot of guys didn't fire their rifle.
because they were too scared.
That was one of the most extraordinary
things that the research about combat....
And a lot of the training was to teach people
how to actually fire their rifle in combat.
You know. it sounds silly.
but a lot of people were too scared to shoot.
-Wasn't it something like 45% ...
-Yeah.
-...or something. in World War II?
In Vietnam. you know.
we all were firing. you know...
and I definitely fired my rifle there.
This is a whole different thing.
These guys are now....
This is that moment
where they're actually getting to release...
all that tension and waiting and anger
and training and everything.
And it's.... Here it is.
They're shooting into the air.
Yeah. It's exhilarating. but it's futile.
And it's not--
-And this look between these two guys...
-It's not what they wanted.
...is really something.
Four days.
Four hours.
You see. we had patrols
longer than this in Vietnam.
And we came back. you know.
talking about that. like....
And I had an.... You know...
so-and-so had an uncle
who is a long-range reconnaissance guy...
who went on 10-day patrols.
You want some beer?
Look here. I got a beer.
The party's started now.
But. you know. the thing is. is that this
parade. then. this sort of sad parade...
and then when this Vietnam vet
gets on the bus...
this to me. I always.... Chokes me up...
when I see this guy.
'cause he could've been a guy I served with.
-Yeah.
-And the way Swoff looks at him...
and Jamie. too. you're thinking. well...
you know. with all his complex emotions.
"Could this be me?"
'Cause the guy thinks they've redeemed him.
We never got a parade in Vietnam.
We never got cheered.
And. you know. these guys have gone off
and won us a clear. triumphant war.
Here's this guy
Swoff and his buddies have redeemed.
This guy's in the Marine Corps
as far as he's concerned.
And this was the beginning of...
for me. really.
the first moment when I tried to attach...
some kind of meaning
to having gone to war...
something other than not having killed.
which was....
Okay. you know. maybe America has learned
this cultural lesson...
and learned to separate the war
from the warrior...
because we didn't do that for this guy.
And. you know.
this Marine vet climbed on our bus...
and at first we were shocked by him.
And as Bill just said. "Oh. could that be me?
Could that be me in 20 years?"
It was important for all of us to see him.
for him to thank us.
And this guy is so good.
I think this is the thing
that I think is so true of us...
that every war is different.
and every war is the same.
Because. you know.
the warrior's experience is so....
And this. we had a lot of voiceover
at the end of here...
that was echoing this theme in Tony's book.
about. just. "Every jarhead is me. "
But it's filmed so beautifully
that we just took it all out because....
And just let the viewer's imagination
fill in the emotion.
Because once that Vietnam vet's in the bus.
I think you just want to watch and feel.
It's a great montage.
just capturing these guys.
You know. this was their future.
-This is Sykes still at war.
-And here's Sykes still at war.
The lifer. still going at it.
Yeah?
These transitions are all very common.
And this. Fergus....
This is another moment...
that there's the guy
that he had the gun to his head.
Yeah. And shoots him.
And they're probably the two
that would get along the most now.
-You know?
-Yeah.
The bearded. scraggily guy
and Swoff the writer...
who. in the Marine Corps.
didn't have a lot in common.
Troy left the Marine Corps.
You know. was forced out. and then died.
The Marine has a love-hate relationship
with the Marine Corps.
That was one of those things we hated
about the Marine Corps...
because they didn't let him stay in.
Of all of us. they should have kept him
in the Marine Corps...
because he loved the Corps so much.
Wanted to make it his life.
And then this story you heard
at the beginning is repeated here...
and you see him.
he's at his word processor.
And it's almost as if he's just told you
the story of the movie...
as he's writing it.
I mean. in a way. this is just a moment
to show that whatever the war gave Tony...
it gave him the material for his first book...
and he became a great writer.
This is Bill's choice here...
on this voiceover. this repetition.
from the beginning and the change.
Yeah. Well. actually. Walter Murch
and Sam and I. we were all working on this.
But I love this.
this bringing these guys back.
I think that was always our idea.
of Sam's and mine. from the beginning.
Because you do feel connected
to all these kids.
I mean. the guys that are out there now.
I feel so much.
I read about them.
not just my son there. but all of them.
The warrior leaves. but he's still fighting.
And then you said a few times. Bill.
there's the biblical sense...
-Being in the desert.
-...of being in the desert.
Yeah. it's not just that we're in
the physical desert of the Middle East...
but that we are wandering in the desert
as Jesus did or the prophets did...
where you're trying to find
who you are and where you belong...
and find your way home.
The desert for me was this landscape.
but also...
when I started writing Jarhead. I had to
enter it again. you know. the physical space.
I surrounded myself
with all of my photos from the war.
I really. for many years.
had avoided that history of mine...
had avoided it personally
and had avoided it as a writer.
But I kept running up against it
and finally could avoid it no longer.
And the desert had always
still been with me.
My memories of the war. of the men.
That last shot of the film
is exactly as I remember the desert.
A small group of men. walking out.
looking for war.
This movie is so specific to that.
I mean. my memories are of the jungle...
which is an entirely different thing.
and it stays with you.
The story that he tells
about turning in the rifle....
I remember walking around for months
feeling strange...
because I wasn't carrying a gun. anymore.
You get so attached to your weapon
in a war. and it becomes...
you know. "This is my rifle.
There are many like it. but this is mine. "
It is the creed of the rifle.
But the thing with this movie is.
that I feel so proud to be part of...
is that it is so true to the experience of...
whether it's my father or my son.
Tony or me.
Regardless of the political context
or even your moral feelings about war...
or particular wars or whatever. the purity.
and I use that word very carefully...
of the young man's. in some cases now
young women's. experience...
is really. I think. to be honoured.
Because what they're willing to do
is so serious and so profound...
that it needs to be called on
by the political leaders...
who send them
in the most serious of all possible ways...
because they truly are on the frontlines.
For those of you who are listening to us.
thank you so much...
and we hope we've made you think...
and given you a new view of these guys
that you might see on your TVscreens...
with their helmets and their goggles...
who are out there
in the middle of nowhere...
prepared to sacrifice and living the life
of an American military guy.
Not just an American.
anyone who does this.
I can't do anything but thank all the people
who helped do that...
from Tony to Sam to the actors
to everybody else...
because it is truly honouring the guys
that go through a passage...
that is both horrible and beautiful
and in every way so confusing...
disturbing and so profoundly human.
Yeah. thanks for listening...
and I hope that the conversation
between Bill and I...
gives you another way to consider the film.
And also to. you know.
consider the men and women...
who serve and sacrifice...
you know. not just during Desert Storm.
but elsewhere and at other times.
The vigour that Bill and I brought
to the telling of the story...
had to do with our personal histories
and trying to tell a story...
that was not just ours.
but that is shared by many.
And so thanks again.
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm